<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-28T16:28:29+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jens Fischer</title><subtitle>A collection of work and ideas on dynamic networks and stochastic population systems</subtitle><author><name>jeMATHfischer</name></author><entry><title type="html">Local Dynamics and Global Impact</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/22/network-segregation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local Dynamics and Global Impact" /><published>2019-01-22T11:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-22T11:20:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/22/network%20segregation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/22/network-segregation.html">&lt;p&gt;Having set the tone in my previous two posts I am happy to now introduce the dynamics enforcing segregation of a graph over time. I am going to describe the local behaviour of each node which can be seen as a single agent and its impacts on the whole structure which takes the form of a graph. You are going to see that just some simple local preference of each agent leads to segregation in the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-MML-AM_CHTML&quot;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;outline-for-a-baseline-model-with-static-world-views&quot;&gt;Outline for a baseline model with static world views&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that the basic setting was a graph consisting of a vertex set &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; and an set of edges &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt;. The vertex set is colored with two colors, such that we have two sets &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_{-1}&lt;/script&gt; such that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V=V_1\cup V_{-1}&lt;/script&gt;.
I am going to sometimes refer to the interpretation that the vertecies of color &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-1&lt;/script&gt; have opinion &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-1&lt;/script&gt;, respectively. This gives me the possibility to talk about actions that each agent performs and might bring the process to a less abstract level. We look at the segregation process in a discrete time scale as mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/19/network-segregation.html&quot;&gt;my previous post &lt;/a&gt;. This is due to the fact that the difficulties that come with the rate at which agents change their relationships are not of interest at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at two agents &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt; we say that edges in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt; display the relations between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/Interacting_agents.png&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image shows a &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt; edge between the two vertices having different colors, namely, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;. All the other edges lead to vertices which are not shown inside the frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
  
    &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/19/network-segregation.html&quot;&gt;&amp;laquo; A Baseline Model&lt;/a&gt;
  
  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Jens</name></author><summary type="html">Having set the tone in my previous two posts I am happy to now introduce the dynamics enforcing segregation of a graph over time. I am going to describe the local behaviour of each node which can be seen as a single agent and its impacts on the whole structure which takes the form of a graph. You are going to see that just some simple local preference of each agent leads to segregation in the network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Baseline Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/19/network-segregation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Baseline Model" /><published>2019-01-19T11:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-19T11:20:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/19/network%20segregation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/19/network-segregation.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I introduce a baseline model for segregation on graphs. In contrast to Schelling’s model which put the agent on the nodes of the grid in the center of attention we will focus on the behaviour of the edges. The edges play the role of a social connection that may be cut if the two end nodes diverge too drastically in their world views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-MML-AM_CHTML&quot;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;outline-for-a-baseline-model-with-static-world-views&quot;&gt;Outline for a baseline model with static world views&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and most simple step is to look at a graph consisting of a vertex set &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V&lt;/script&gt; and an set of edges &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt;. We then color the vertex set in two colors, i.e., we have two sets &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_{-1}&lt;/script&gt; such that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V=V_1\cup V_{-1}&lt;/script&gt;.
We can interpret the vertecies of color &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-1&lt;/script&gt; as having opinion &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-1&lt;/script&gt;, respectively. This is a very simplified model since our population can be sperated into two distinct opinions but it can serve as a baseline model.
The edges &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;E&lt;/script&gt; then display the relations between two individuals given by some vertices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/bimodal_population_init.png&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;color: blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; edges between the &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; vertices in the preceding picture depict relations between individuals of identical opinion &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;, respectively. They are not prone to conflict because both individuals are perfectly aligned.
In contrast to them the &lt;span style=&quot;color: red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt; edges are those that display a conflict. They connect individuals who have different opinions displayed by the vertices having different colors.&lt;br /&gt;
There are two possible ways to go forth in the modelling procedure.
First, we could think of an agreement process where both individuals find common ground and the conflict is resolved. Within the framework of two possible opinions agreement is only possible if one of the individuals takes the opinion of the other, i.e., one of the vertices swaps the color. This process does not lead to segregation but to the spread of one opinion and fits rather in the setting of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_drift&quot;&gt;Wright-Fisher type models&lt;/a&gt;. We are going to come back to this process later on in the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/contagion.gif&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the last model could not capture segregation we focus on a different approach. In this cas the conflicts are resolved by breaking up the relationships between the individuals of different opinion. This will necessarily lead to segregation. But what happens if we allow forming of new relationships to compensate for the broken one? This is going to be our baseline model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;segregation-in-the-baseline-model&quot;&gt;Segregation in the baseline model&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proposed baseline model shows the following dynamical behaviour of our population given by a graph. This graph consists of &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; vertices as well as &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;green&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt; edges. 
The process runs in discrete time, so starting from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t=0&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t=1&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t=2&lt;/script&gt; and so on. In each step we erase a &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt; edge and connect one of its end points randomly to another vertex. The process stops as soon as there are &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;no&lt;/span&gt; more &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;red&lt;/span&gt; edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/baseline_flip.gif&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the upcoming posts I am first going to discuss the concrete model and its mathematical properties. Afterwards we are going to look at the convergence behaviour to then advance the model to more opinions and therefore colors. Thus, with each subsequent post the complexity is going to increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you on my next post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline text-align:left&quot;&gt;
  
    &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/01/17/network-segregation.html&quot;&gt;&amp;laquo; Randomized Network Segregation&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;&gt;
  
    &lt;a class=&quot;next&quot; href=&quot;/2019/01/22/network-segregation.html&quot;&gt;Local Dynamics and Global Impact &amp;raquo;&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Jens</name></author><summary type="html">In this post I introduce a baseline model for segregation on graphs. In contrast to Schelling’s model which put the agent on the nodes of the grid in the center of attention we will focus on the behaviour of the edges. The edges play the role of a social connection that may be cut if the two end nodes diverge too drastically in their world views.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Randomized Network Segregation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/17/network-segregation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Randomized Network Segregation" /><published>2019-01-17T11:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-17T11:20:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/17/network%20segregation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/17/network-segregation.html">&lt;p&gt;Racial and religious segregation is an issue known from many parts of the world. Even if there are no laws in state enforcing segregation it might still happen due to the history and social structure of the area. &lt;br /&gt;
While historically segregation is a behaviour that shows its effects explicitly within the communities modern segregation through social media might not be visible in one neighborhood. This situation demands new models for non-geographically constraint segregation. I am going to discuss some of my ideas within this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;schellings-segregation-model&quot;&gt;Schelling’s Segregation model&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Schelling proposed in 1971 a model to discribe the ethnical segregation in the larger cities of the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/chicago_seg.jpg&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His agent based model showed that segregation also happens if the agents do not mind living next to agents of different kind. 
The basic concept was to put the agents on the nodes of a grid and allow in every time step a transition according to their current preference. 
One agent A’s current preference was thereby defined as the proportion of agents of similar or dissimilar kind surrounding A. 
If the proportion dropped below a fixed threshhold then A starts to move on the grid trying to improve the proportion.
A gameified simulation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncase.me/polygons/&quot;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;segregation-of-networks&quot;&gt;Segregation of Networks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main dynamics of Schelling’s model is given by the agent’s movement along the grid on which they are placed. Their movement is therefore inherently constrained by the structure of their environement.
When considering networks that connect agents which are not subject to this constraint, e.g., social networks on the internet, Schelling’s model is no longer applicable. Nonetheless, we observe segregation in these networks where connections are given up due to diverging values or political views.
During this series I want to present a basic model for segregation in networks on which I am currently working on and hope to give live updates on the results. 
During the first few posts I am going to present my simplest model and introduce some extensions always paired with some simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;html&gt;
  
  
    &lt;a class=&quot;next&quot; href=&quot;/2019/01/19/network-segregation.html&quot;&gt;A Baseline Model &amp;raquo;&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Jens</name></author><summary type="html">Racial and religious segregation is an issue known from many parts of the world. Even if there are no laws in state enforcing segregation it might still happen due to the history and social structure of the area. While historically segregation is a behaviour that shows its effects explicitly within the communities modern segregation through social media might not be visible in one neighborhood. This situation demands new models for non-geographically constraint segregation. I am going to discuss some of my ideas within this series.</summary></entry></feed>